Finding Aid for University of Michigan. Office of International Academic Affairs, Records
Bentley Historical Library
Office of International Academic Affairs (University of Michigan), records
1968-1993
1989-1992
Bentley Historical Library
University of Michigan. Office of International Academic Affairs.
9478 Bimu 2
5.8 linear feet (in 7 boxes)
University of Michigan unit established in 1990 concerned with the university's international research and teaching activities. Series in the record group include: Presidential Initiatives Fund, Units, Topical Files, Correspondence, and Visual Materials including photographs and videocassettes primarily depicting visit of University of Michigan delegation to South Africa in 1991 in part to present honorary degree to Nelson Mandela.
The records were transferred by the Office of International Academic Affairs (donor no. 8175 ).
The collection is open for research.
In 1988 inaugural address, University of Michigan President James Duderstadt highlighted the importance of the university's international role. International initiatives at the university, from 1988 to 1993, were carried out under the administrative offices of the Associate Vice President for International Academic Affairs and the Office of International Academic Affairs, and by various advisory committees such as the Committee on International Studies, the University Council on International Academic Affairs (UCIAA), and the International Studies Advisory Council. In September 1988 President Duderstadt named University of Michigan Law Professor, John H. Jackson Associate Vice President of Academic Affairs in charge of international activities, to head the Office of International Academic Affairs. Jackson was charged with providing coordination of and increasing visibility for the international programs on campus.
The UCIAA, established in 1990, was charged with "encouraging and strengthening the international components of the teaching and research agendas." The UCIAA was responsible for approving grants awarded by the Presidential Initiative Funds for international activities such as support for visiting scholars. Harold K. Jacobson took over in January 1990 as Interim Associate Vice President for International Affairs.
For the period 1990-1993, Ruth G. Hastie was director of International Academic Affairs, under the Associate Vice President for International Affairs.
In September 1993, the Office of International Academic Affairs was consolidated with the Institute for Foreign Area and International Studies to become the International Institute located within the College of Literature, Science and the Arts. The director of the new institute is David W. Cohen.
The records of the Office of International Academic Affairs document the international affairs and concerns of the University of Michigan. The records span the years 1968-1993; the bulk of the materials cover 1989-1992. The records are divided into five series: Presidential Initiatives Fund, Academic Units, Topical Files, Correspondence, and Visual Materials
Area studies -- Michigan.; Educational exchanges.; Exchange of persons programs.; International education -- Michigan.; Teacher exchange programs.; South Africa -- Description and travel.; Photographs.; Videotapes.; University of Michigan. Office of International Academic Affairs.; Mandela, Nelson, 1918-2013.; University of Michigan. Office of International Academic Affairs.
- Presidential Initiatives Fund
  The Presidential Initiatives Fund series (1 linear foot) documents the allocation of funds used to support international scholarship and education through exchanges, visiting scholars, and travel programs. The "Background" files contain the proposal requests that were submitted to the Committee on International Studies. The "Commitment Summary" folders contain a listing of the funding recipients, amount of money awarded, and a brief description of the proposed project. Within the "Executive Committee Report," the researcher will find a breakdown of PIF allocations by campus unit.
  - General, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Allocations, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Background Documents
    - 1989-1990, 8 folders (Box 1)
    - 1990-1991, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Budget
    - Analysis, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - Planning, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - Report
      - 1989-1990 (Box 1)
      - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Commitment Letters, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Commitment Summary
    - 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Final Log
    - 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Fund Information, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Funding Guidelines
    - 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee Report, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - W.K. Kellogg Foundation, 1989-1991 (Box 1)
- Academic Units
  The Academic Units series (1.2 linear feet) contains information that was gathered on many of the university international and area studies centers. Included within the files is information concerning the goals and purpose of the centers, international affiliations, and a calendar of events, in addition to information on programs and special projects.
  - AfroAmerican and African Studies, Center for (CAAS), 1987-1991 (Box 2)
  - Armenian Studies Program, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Asian Studies, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Chinese Studies, Center for
    - General, 1988-1990 (Box 2)
    - Asia Pacific Rim Proposal, 1987-1990 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1989-1991 (Box 2)
    - Masters Degree Recipients, 1948-1988 (Box 2)
    - Taiwan Initiatives, 1988-1991 (Box 2)
    - Title VI Proposal, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Dutch Studies Program
    - General, 1983-1985 (Box 2)
    - Dutch Lecturer, 1976-1988 (Box 2)
    - Dutch Writer in Residence, 1980-1989 (Box 2)
    - Netherlands American University League, 1981-1983 (Box 2)
    - Netherlands Government Commitment, 1947
      - General, 1984-1989; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Netherlands Visiting Professor
      - Professor A.A. Derksin, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Professor S.P. Gradstein, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
      - Dr. Sancisi, 1987-1991 (Box 2)
      - Professor S.R. Slings, 1987-1992 (Box 2)
  - German Studies Program
    - Centers of Excellence, 1989 (Box 2)
    - German Academic Exchange Service (DAAD) (visiting professorship), 1990-1992 (Box 2)
    - Proposals, 1989 (Box 2)
  - International Business Education, Center for
    - General, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Advisory Committee, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Advisory Council, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Annual Report, 1990Area Studies (Box 2)
    - APEC, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - Poland
      - Michigan Business Assistance Corps for (FIPSE), 1990/91 (Box 2)
      - Management and Business Education for (TEMPUS), 1990 (Box 2)
    - Title VI Proposal, 1990-1992 (Box 2)
  - Japanese Studies, Center for
    - General, 1988-1992 (Box 2)
    - International Automotive Industry Forum, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Masters Degree Recipients, 1946-1988 (Box 2)
    - Outreach, 1972-1985 (Box 2)
    - Toyota Visiting Professorship, 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - Korean Studies
    - General, 1990-1993 (Box 2)
    - Fund Raising Dinner, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Hyuck-In Low Visit, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Latin American and Caribbean Studies, 1989-1993 (Box 2)
  - Near Eastern and North African Studies, Center for, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - Russian and East European Studies, Center for (CREES)
    - General, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
    - Advisory Council, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Copernicus Endowment, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1987-1991 (Box 2)
    - Title VI Proposal, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - South and Southeast Asian Studies (SSEAS)
    - General, 1989-1992 (Box 3)
    - Business Program, 1988-1992 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1982-1988 (Box 3)
    - Department of Education Proposal, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Luce Foundation, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Sikh Studies, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Title VI Proposal, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Swiss Area Studies, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Western European Studies, Center for (CWES), 1968-1990 (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series (1.8 linear feet) is comprised of the administrative files of the office. There are many files relating to committees or groups with international concerns. A Michigan Vision: International Studies at University of Michigan (found under the heading "Report") contains information on the international history of the university and potential goals for the future. The files also contain additional information on Area Studies Centers.
  - Academic Affairs Advisory Council (AAAC), 1989 (Box 3)
  - Academic Policy Group (APG)
    - General, 1987-1989 (Box 3)
    - Area Studies Centers Discussion, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Afghanistan, 1989-1993 (Box 3)
  - Area Studies Centers
    - General, 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - Administrative Review, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Budget Materials, 1985-1992 (Box 3)
    - Capital Campaign, 1984-1986 (Box 3)
    - Paper: Area Studies, Issues and Concerns, (Harold K. Jacobson), 1992 (Box 3)
    - Outline: Tracing the Development of Area Studies at University of Michigan, (Ruth Hastie), 1991 (Box 3)
    - Reorganization Discussion, 1985-1986 (Box 3)
    - Study Group, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Budget Materials
    - 1989/90 (Box 3)
    - 1990/91 (Box 3)
    - 1991/92 (Box 3)
  - China
    - General, 1984-1993 (Box 3)
    - Committee for Chinese-American Scientific Exchange, 1990-1992 (Box 3)
  - Chinese Student Crisis, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Commitment Letters, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Committee to Examine Area Centers, Report of, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Committee on International Studies
    - Meeting Minutes, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    - Membership, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    - Purpose and Goals, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Report to Kellogg Foundation, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Steering Committee, 1987-1990 (Box 3)
  - Commonwealth of Independent States (former Soviet Union)
    - General, 1989-1991 (Box 3)
    - Russian American University Consortium, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Wilhem, John (re: business and economic training), 1989-1992 (Box 3)
  - Deans' Meetings (re: internationalization), 1990 (Box 3)
  - Duderstadt, James J. (President of University of Michigan), 1990 (Box 3)
  - Executive Committee Visits, (re: internationalism), 1990-1992 (Box 3)
  - Faculty Advisory Committee on International Programs (FACIP) (report of), 1968 (Box 3)
  - Ford Foundation (international studies funding), 1966-1968 (Box 3)
  - Germany, 1989-1992 (Box 3)
  - Gosling Report (institute proposal), 1965 (Box 3)
  - Harvard-Michigan-MIT Meeting (international relations of universities)
    - General, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Background Information, 1990/91 (Box 3)
  - Hungary, 1989-1992 (Box 3)
  - Institute for International Studies (proposal for), 1989 (Box 4)
  - Inter-Center Council (ICC)
    - General, 1990/91 (Box 4)
    - Faculty Retreat, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1991/2 (Box 4)
  - International Studies, Committee on, 1990 (Box 4)
  - International Studies Advisory Council (ISAC)
    - Membership, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Meetings, 1990 (Box 4)
  - International Visitors, 1990/91 (Box 4)
  - Internationalization Issues (re: University of Michigan), 1990 (Box 4)
  - Jackson, James S. Associate Dean, Graduate School (re: international graduate education), 1992 (Box 4)
  - Jackson, John H., Associate Vice President for Academic Affairs, 1987-1989 (Box 4)
  - Jacobson, Harold K., Interim Associate Vice President of International Academic Affairs, 1989-1992 (Box 4)
  - Japan, 1987-1992 (Box 4)
  - May Symposium
    - Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
    - Ford Foundation Proposal, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
    - Publicity, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Symposium Schedules, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Midwest Universities Consortium for International Activities (MUCIA), 1989 (Box 4)
  - Mexico, 1991-1993 (Box 4)
  - National Resource Centers (NRC) Title VI Allocations
    - 1988-1990 (Box 4)
    - 1990-1992 (Box 4)
  - Philippines (Abueva visit), 1992 (Box 4)
  - Po, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Program for Inter-International Collaboration in Area Studies (PICAS)
    - General, 1988-1992 (Box 4)
    - Annual Reports, 1986-1991 (Box 4)
  - Rackham Travel Grants, 1990/91 (Box 4)
  - Report
    - A Michigan Vision: International Studies at University of Michigan by John J. Jackson, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Responses to, 1989 (Box 4)
  - South Africa, 1992 (Box 4)
  - South African Educational Programs (IIE), 1985-1989 (Box 4)
  - Strategy Planning (re: internationalism), 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - Swain, Mary Ann (International Activities Report), 1986 (Box 4)
  - Switzer, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Taiwan, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
  - University Council for International Academic Affairs (UCIAA)
    - General, 1990/91 (Box 4)
    - Advisory Committee Meeting, 1988-1992 (Box 4)
    - Advisory Committee Membership, 1988/89 (Box 4)
    - Executive Committee Meeting, 1990-1992; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - University Council for International Programs (proposal), 1990 (Box 4)
  - Whitaker, Gilbert R. (Provost & Vice President for Academic Affairs), 1990 (Box 4)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (1.4 linear feet) is arranged in chronological order. The series is comprised of out-going memos, letters, and e-mail that were generated by the Office of International Academic Affairs. Any in-coming mail will be found stapled to the response. The researcher will find funding information, memos to the UCIAA Executive Committee, and information regarding various programs and events of an international nature that relate to the university.
  - 1988-1989
    - Chronological (Box 5)
    - A-Z (Box 5)
    - Vest, Charles, (incoming) (Box 5)
  - 1989-1990
    - Chronological (Box 5)
    - A-F (Box 5)
    - G-M (Box 5)
    - N-Z (Box 5)
    - E-mail (Box 5)
    - Vest, Charles (incoming) (Box 5)
  - 1990-1991
    - July (Box 5)
    - September (Box 5)
    - October (Box 5)
    - November (Box 5)
    - December (Box 5)
    - January (Box 5)
    - February (Box 5)
    - March (Box 5)
    - April (Box 5)
    - May (Box 5)
    - June (Box 5)
  - 1991-1992
    - July (Box 5)
    - August (Box 5)
    - September (Box 5)
    - October (Box 5)
    - November (Box 5)
    - December (Box 5)
    - January (Box 6)
    - March (Box 6)
    - April (Box 6)
    - May (Box 6)
    - June (Box 6)
  - 1992-1993
    - July (Box 6)
    - August (Box 6)
    - September (Box 6)
    - October (Box 6)
    - November (Box 6)
    - December (Box 6)
    - January (Box 6)
    - February (Box 6)
    - March (Box 6)
    - April (Box 6)
    - May (Box 6)
    - June (Box 6)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series (.4 linear feet) consists of twelve VHS format videos and color photographs, including photographs of Nelson Mandela. The videos document the twelve-day visit to South Africa by a University of Michigan delegation in September 1991. The delegation consisted of Harold Jacobson, Interim Associate Vice Provost for International Academic Affairs; Earl Lewis, Director of the Center for Afro American and African Studies; Charles D. Moody, Sr., Vice Provost for Minority Affairs; and Moffat Mogane, a Ph.D. candidate in Social Work and Psychology. The goals of the trip were threefold: to meet with administrators and faculty to gather information and to consider the possibility of establishing mutually beneficial academic relationships with the University of Michigan and South African educational institutions; to explore how the University of Michigan could usefully contribute to the education of Black South Africans; and to explore the possibility of joint or parallel studies of "race" and race relations, and institutional transformation in multi racial societies. During this trip, the Michigan delegation met with Nelson Mandela and presented him with the honorary Doctor of Laws degree that was originally awarded in absentia in 1987.
  - Videos (VHS format)
    - EEOC (Box 7)
    - London (Box 7)
    - Mandela, Nelson (receiving award) (Box 7)
    - Radio Interview (Box 7)
    - University of Cape Town (Box 7)
    - University of Durban-Westville (Box 7)
    - University of Ft. Hare (Box 7)
    - University of Natal #1 (Box 7)
    - University of Natal #2 (Box 7)
    - University of the North (Box 7)
    - University of Western Cape (Box 7)
    - University of WITS (Box 7)
  - Photographs of Nelson Mandela accepting honorary degree., 8 photographs (color) (Box 7)